<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Life | Ranting @ 741 MHz]]></title>
  <link href="http://741MHz.com/blog/categories/life/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://741MHz.com/"/>
  <updated>2013-12-08T13:38:51-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://741MHz.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[741MHz.com]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Coding While Hungover]]></title>
    <link href="http://741MHz.com/coding-hungover/"/>
    <updated>2013-12-07T16:03:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://741MHz.com/coding-hungover</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Hooked up with Bender last night and woke up with a gong banging in your head? Have to work today, used up all of your sick days and calling in dead is not an option? Welcome to the club! Now you have to get up and drag your sick body to work. But the biggest challenge today is to survive long working hours. We’ve put up a few tips to help you do just that.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/coding-hungover/admin-spit-zarplata-idet.jpg"></p>

<h2>Shower</h2>

<p>A good shower helps you feel better, clean and refreshed. It helps even more during hangover by washing off toxins that your body’s <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Excretory_system">excretory system</a> flushes out though the largest organ of your body, your <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Skin">skin</a>. Of course, body does it all the time, but the amount of toxins is increased during the next day or two after drinking. So don’t make today an exception and take a shower. But before you start singing your favorite tune while washing off the toxins, ensure a normal water temperature. Water too hot or too cold might put an extra stress on your body, so maintaining a moderate temperature might help avoid further complications.</p>

<h2>Hydrate</h2>

<p>Your whole body including the brain is sucked dry. <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dehydration">Dehydration</a> may cause thirst, dry mouth, dizziness and other unpleasant phenomena. To help your body get rid of <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ethanol">ethanol</a> and <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Acetaldehyde">acetaldehyde</a>, consider constantly refilling your body&rsquo;s water supplies.</p>

<p>Beware that some online sources recommend drinking coconut water. That’s a trap! It is well known that <a href="http://www.livestrong.com/article/488081-does-drinking-coconut-water-cause-diarrhea/">coconut water can cause a diarrhea</a> in some people – the last thing you need right now.</p>

<p>For better results, you may want to drink mineral water or orange juice for some <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Citric_acid">Citric Acid</a> and Vitamin C. If you decide to go for a juice, make sure you get a natural one. Stay away from supermarket solutions <a href="http://www.care2.com/causes/why-are-all-natural-labels-disappearing-from-many-popular-foods.html">even if they read “all natural”</a>. Make sure you either make the juice yourself from the fresh oranges or you witness the process.</p>

<p>Keep the fluid supply coming throughout the day.</p>

<h2>Detox</h2>

<h3>PainKillers</h3>

<p>Avoid taking aspirin, ibuprofen or similar painkillers including special brands like Alka-Seltzer. Instead of helping you, liver killers <a href="http://www.readabstracts.com/Health/Aspirin-increases-blood-alcohol-concentrations-in-humans-after-ingestion-of-ethanol.html">have an opposite effect</a> and make you feel worse by putting extra load on your liver, increasing blood alcohol concentration and making it harder for you to recover.</p>

<p>Try to stay off drinking caffeine and smoking cigarettes as well, those only make things worse.</p>

<p>Of course, the headache may be so severe that you’d rather chop off your head to stop the sufferings. If that’s the case, you may want to take some aspiring to get through the day. But don&rsquo;t take too much.</p>

<h3>Charcoal Activated</h3>

<p><a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B005WZ5REC/ref=as_li_tf_il?ie=UTF8&camp=1789&creative=9325&creativeASIN=B005WZ5REC&linkCode=as2&tag=ra74mh-20"><img class="right <a" src="href="http://ws-na.amazon-adsystem.com/widgets/q?_encoding=UTF8&amp;ASIN=B005WZ5REC&amp;Format=_SL110_&amp;ID=AsinImage&amp;MarketPlace=US&amp;ServiceVersion=20070822&amp;WS=1&amp;tag=ra74mh-20">http://ws-na.amazon-adsystem.com/widgets/q?_encoding=UTF8&amp;ASIN=B005WZ5REC&amp;Format=_SL110_&amp;ID=AsinImage&amp;MarketPlace=US&amp;ServiceVersion=20070822&amp;WS=1&amp;tag=ra74mh-20</a>"></a><img src="http://ir-na.amazon-adsystem.com/e/ir?t=ra74mh-20&l=as2&o=1&a=B005WZ5REC" width="1" height="1" border="0" alt="" style="border:none !important; margin:0px !important;" /> The best pill to take during hangover is activated charcoal. It helps your body detox a lot quicker. It is also known as activated carbon or activated coal. You can get this finest natural absorbent agent without over the counter in your local pharmacy or online.</p>

<h2>Eat Up</h2>

<p><img class="right" src="/images/coding-hungover/winnie-eats-honey.jpg"> When hung over, make sure you are not a diet. Do not limit yourself and try to consume at least half of your daily calories in this meal. There are certain foods recommended when coping with hangover because they help restore resources your body needs the most at a moment.</p>

<ul>
<li>Honey. Bee’s gift to humankind helps your fructose levels. If you cannot eat it like Winnie Pooh, you can add it to your tea or warm boiling water for a more diluted and less sweet way to consume honey.</li>
<li>Bananas help to restore potassium in your body that was washed off by increased diuresis last night.</li>
<li>Soups and eggs might help to bring in vitamins and amino acids as well.</li>
</ul>


<p>Some people recommend eating a few raw eggs — we would recommend to keep away from those. Technically they may help to cure a hangover, but they are also a great source of salmonella, which is a lot worse than a hangover. So do not bear unnecessary risks.</p>

<p>And of course beacon. Beacon is great under all circumstances.</p>

<h2>Hair of the dog</h2>

<p>No matter what happens – do not drink more. There is a big difference between hangover and alcohol withdrawal syndrome. The first is pretty normal for most healthy people. The second is what happens to alcoholics when they stop drinking. If you dare to drink while hungover, you would pretty much make a big step forward towards alcoholism.</p>

<p>This is of course not to mention that being drunk at work is not illegal per se, but most company have a special section in work contract that you have signed that pretty much says they can fire you right away for being drunk. It is a lot better to appear tired at work rather than a drunken idiot who gets fired.</p>

<h2>Avoid Working</h2>

<p>Since you are an engineer, chances are that you love what you are doing. Try to avoid doing things you do not like. If you have a large piece of software to code or a list of important changes to make, find something else to do today.</p>

<p>Try to participate in more meetings, especially those in which you are not supposed to give a speech. Checking out your coworker’s meeting schedules might help you find a way to spend an hour or two without coding, and you might as well learn something new and interesting.</p>

<h3>Ask Others For Help</h3>

<p>Even if you are a rockstar programmer and know everything better than others, asking a colleague to explain software architecture, pretend you cannot wrap your head around some piece of logic and ask to help you write it, or even ask to walk you through your colleagues productivity workflow tricks like his or her favorite editor and its capability would certainly be your smart moves.</p>

<p>This may let you sit back and listen for a while instead of staring at your code. It will also make you build stronger relationships with your colleagues. Remember – people love when others ask them questions. They love when others ask them to help. It makes them feel important. Social creatures.</p>

<iframe src="http://embed.ted.com/talks/amanda_palmer_the_art_of_asking.html" width="640" height="360" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" webkitAllowFullScreen mozallowfullscreen allowFullScreen></iframe>


<h3>Minimize The Damage</h3>

<p>If you still must write some code, try to minimize the damage. Before you start, make sure everything that you do not screw up the code you wrote a day before. Chances are that what you have written a day before is better than what you are about to craft while sick.</p>

<p>The first step is to check what changes are uncommitted. You risk losing your work by not checking for that. Not because of a hard drive failure, but because it might be very difficult to distinguish good code from bad later.</p>

<p>The more you have uncommitted is better. But do not rush to commit just yet. There might have been something unfinished that you don’t quite remember about. But most importantly, this code might be your ticket to doing nothing today as you can commit it by the end of day and pretend you were working hard all day.</p>

<p>So instead of committing, make a private backup copy (or two). Then focus on making this code look better. Apply some code refactoring and unit testing skills, add more features, have fun. You can always run the diff tool against directory (diff –dru) to see what you have changed. If confident enough, commit your work by the end of the day. If not, leave it for tomorrow. You can always say you forgot to do that – no biggie.</p>

<h2>Take A Nap</h2>

<p>If possible, try to use some time for a nap. Lunch hour might be a good opportunity for that. If you do not have a safe place in your office and hiding in the closet does not sound like a good idea, make sure to schedule a spa session in a nearby saloon. You can always tell them you just want to sleep – nobody cares as long as you pay for a session (and what if they are hungoever, too?). Just don’t forget to ask for a wake up call or your colleagues might start worrying if you never come back.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.kickstarter.com/projects/ostrich-pillow/ostrich-pillow"><img class="center" src="/images/coding-hungover/ostrich-pillow.jpg"></a></p>

<h2>Take a Dump</h2>

<p><img class="right" src="/images/coding-hungover/bender-poops.gif"> Take a dump. You won’t find this advice at other places online a lot. We don&rsquo;t know whether this is because of censorships or authors not feeling confident enough to talk about hangover shit. But we assure you — taking a good dump is one of the most effective ways to cure a hangover as it helps the body get rid of the toxins. For obvious reasons, we recommend you take this step first, even before showering. The only reason why this does not appear as the first advice is to not scare off some readers right away.</p>

<h2>Don&rsquo;t Mention</h2>

<p>Unless of course it was a corporate party or a casual &ldquo;getting hammered&rdquo; Thursday night with your colleagues, never mention that you have a hangover. That’s simply not the way to get others to sympathize; it works the other way around.</p>

<p>Try to look fresh, use some eye drops to reduce redness, make sure to brush your teeth every one-two hours to have a fresh breath, and if somebody asks if you are OK, tell you have a migraine.</p>

<h2>Pray</h2>

<p>In case you accidentally fall asleep at work and somebody wakes you up, immediately say &ldquo;Amen. Sorry I was praying.&rdquo; Nobody in their right mind would have anything against you pray. We have a <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Freedom_of_religion">freedom of religion</a>, after all.</p>

<p>And remember, the best way to fight a hangover is to not drink alcohol in a first place.</p>

<p>As always, thanks for reading!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Ask Smart Questions And You Will Succeed]]></title>
    <link href="http://741MHz.com/ask-smart/"/>
    <updated>2013-03-29T22:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://741MHz.com/ask-smart</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Asking is ultimately one of the most important ways for you to succeed. You shall not be afraid to ask. You shall ask often. Ask for help and for a raise, ask for an advice and ask questions. Asking is very powerful. Not only it might help you to get an answer, you may as well receive something that is a lot more valuable, something you haven’t even thought of before. Asking helps you to make your way. It helps others to understand you better. Asking connects people. In English we say, “It doesn’t hurt to ask.” Russians say, “Nobody punches your nose for asking.” I am sure that other cultures have a similar saying.</p>

<p>I have been hanging out on <a href="http://stackoverflow.com/">Stack Overflow</a>, a nice Q&amp;A site, for about two years now, and have answered some 770 questions. Not a lot, but I have enjoyed each and every question I have either answered or at least tried to answer. Yet my questions are what I am proud of the most. They were most helpful, at least for me. Sometimes, answering a question creates more questions and leads to a research, helps to learn something new — be that a programming trick, a new technology, a new interesting person that you didn’t know before. It is always better to ask than not to ask. In any case it makes you richer.</p>

<p>OK, now it sounds like a crap from a cheap inspiration book. Things cannot be that simple. Indeed there is a catch to asking — just asking doesn’t really get you anywhere. You want people to be interested in your question, you want the question to be wise, you want your question to make others think, and oftentimes you want your question to be answered.</p>

<blockquote><p>Whoever said “there’s no such thing as a bad question” clearly had never seen the Internet.<br/>
— <a href="https://twitter.com/AndrewLBarber">Andrew Barber</a></p></blockquote>

<p>There ain’t no such thing as a free lunch. And just like with everything else, in order for your questions to make you successful, some efforts from you are required. Of course nobody knows everything, and there is absolutely nothing wrong with saying, “I don’t know”. But you must at least show some efforts, some respect to those who read the question, or those who have already answered it million times over. There is a lot of great information about how to ask smart questions, and just in case you haven’t read it already, below are some links to a great tutorials about how to ask great questions. Trust me, you won’t waste your time by reading them. Those tutorials will definitely help you to succeed whatever your goals are:</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="http://www.catb.org/esr/faqs/smart-questions.html">How To Ask Questions The Smart Way</a> by Eric Steven Raymond</li>
<li><a href="http://www.forbes.com/sites/stevedenning/2011/09/11/learning-to-ask-the-right-question-2/">Learning To Ask The Right Question</a> by Steve Denning, Forbes</li>
<li><a href="http://mattgemmell.com/2008/12/08/what-have-you-tried/">What have You tried so far?</a> by Matt Gemmell</li>
<li><a href="http://www.youngbloodcoaching.com/powerful-questions.html">The Art of Asking Powerful Questions</a></li>
</ul>


<p>And if you are looking for the right place to ask your questions online, you might find one of the <a href="http://stackexchange.com/">Stack Exchange Q&amp;A sites</a> very useful. Whether you are into LEGO, Marital Arts, Politics or Physics, interested in Chemistry, or History, or the history of chemistry, or whatever that is you are interested in – there is a web site for it.</p>

<p><a href="http://stackexchange.com/"><img src="/images/stack-exchange-top-sites.png"></a></p>

<p>Hope it helps. Good Luck!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Stranded]]></title>
    <link href="http://741MHz.com/stranded/"/>
    <updated>2013-03-23T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://741MHz.com/stranded</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>One of the things I really love about WordPress.com is its community. The Daily Prompt movement is especially great — it helps to connect so many people together, share so many great stories, and ideas. I am relatively new to blogging in general and WordPress in particular, so most of the time I just enjoy good reads. But today’s Daily Prompt’s topic “Stranded” brought back some of my old good memories and I decided to share my story about how I got stranded in a foreign city for a few days with no money and no friends.</p>

<p>I have lived in New York area for a while now. But I am an immigrant, so I wasn’t always here. My life journey started in Illichivsk — a small half-resort, half-port city on the shores of the Black Sea, named after Vladimir Lenin. I was born there, in a country that does not exist anymore — USSR. In 1991, USSR fell apart, Ukraine got its independence, and I acquired a Ukrainian citizenship.</p>

<p>The Illichivsk is a very small town. Back in the day there was no public transportation, no universities, no businesses, no jobs, no nothing. To say that it has always been extremely hard to make a living there is to say nothing at all. Both of my parents were working from dusk till dawn, and the income was barely enough to buy groceries. Everything was pretty much dead all year around except for the summers. I loved summers. It was a great chance for me to make some pocket-money. I used to buy some ice cream in the town, put it into a backpack and rush to the beach to sell it to lazy tourists. I would make enough money to buy an ice cream for my crush. Usually boys buy movie tickets and flowers, but we had no cinemas in Illichivsk. And flowers I used to steal from somebody’s lawn.</p>

<p>One day my parents bought me a computer despite the fear that I would start playing video games all the time — they believed that computer would help me study. It worked out great — instead of playing video games I got into programming. First thing I installed on my computer was FreeBSD — operating system that somebody recommended to me in a local bookstore. It did not support my video card so I was working in console, 100% text mode. I got an English dictionary and translated manual pages word by word. That is pretty much how I learned to understand English and got my first experience with UNIX. I also bought a few Russian books about C programming and after about a year of studying day and night I started working as a freelancer taking on simple programming gigs. It was not paying a lot. But it was enough for me to quit my seasonal ice cream sales business.</p>

<p>I always knew that to achieve something in my life I had to get out of that town. And by the time I was finishing the high school I sent my résumé to pretty much every company in Ukraine that I could find. Most of them never got back. But one day I got a phone call from Miratech — a big outsourcing company with headquarters in Kiev — the capital of Ukraine. Boy was I excited. The bags got packed with a speed of light, the piggy bank crushed to finance the trip, and I hopped on the next train to Kiev to get to a job interview, before my parents could understand what is going on.</p>

<p>I was hired. I was excited. It felt great. I will never forget that moment, those overwhelming feelings, that small success, an achievement, a coincidence, a chance that I was given. There was only one small problem — you don’t get paid until the end of the month, and I haven’t even started yet. I had no money. I had no friends. I was a kid all by myself in the big city that I knew absolutely nothing about. Where do I go; what do I do? I was stranded.</p>

<p>Having no other choice, I immediately called my parents for help. They could have sent some money and have me return home. But going home was not an option for me — it would have been a huge step back. I had different goals. I wanted to show up at work next day, make a career and settle in Kiev. My parents knew that, and so they took last $300 of family money that we had and my father hopped on the next train to Kiev to help me out. The idea was to rent an apartment for $150 (for one month), buy a ticket so he can go back home. And leave the rest to me so I can buy some food and go to work.</p>

<p>Frankly speaking that was a very brave, naïve and indeed optimistic move. After my dad arrived on the scene, we spent the whole day rushing from one place to another trying to find an apartment. But nothing was up for rent for the money we had. A few apartments that we could afford were so far from the city that the only way to get to work for me would have been to drive a car, which I didn’t have. After a day of rat-running from one part of the city to another, we ended up in the middle of nowhere. It was 11 PM — too late to search for anything. We stood right there. We were hungry and freezing. We have stranded in a foreign city with no money and no friends. Where do we go; what do we do?</p>

<p>The thought of giving up and going home has crossed my mind many times. Perhaps my father thought about that too, but he never said anything like that. Instead, he was telling me not to worry, that we would find the way out. Though of course he had no idea what to do either. We were about to go to the train terminal, try to sleep there and resume our journey in the early morning.
Semiconscious, I was going through my phone’s address book looking for at least someone I could ask for help. But whom can I send an S.O.S. if I don’t know anyone who lives anywhere close? Suddenly, my eyes stopped on the entry that said “The Key”, and a phone number. What does it mean, whose phone number is that? Flashback. I remembered — a few months ago I was talking online on #rain IRC channel with a girl whose nickname was “key”. I told her that I would love to move to Kiev one day, if I ever get a chance. And she gave me her number just in case I get in trouble and would need help. I didn’t even know her name, but called the number. I said, — “Hello, this is Vlad, the kid from IRC chat. We met online, remember? I am here, uhm… I am not sure where I am exactly, I am here with my daddy, and we don’t know what to do… can you help us? Please.”</p>

<p>I don’t know if she remembered me or not. She quickly asked what do we see in order to pinpoint our location, instructed us to get on a subway, told which train to take, what stop we should get off, and promised to meet us there. When we arrived, she was waiting for us, accompanied by quite big, nice and very beautiful dog — that was for her own protection, because you never know. “Hello, I’m Dasha. Follow me,” she said. My dad and me said “Hi,” introduced ourselves and started to tell our story while walking to her apartment.</p>

<p>When we arrived, Dasha poured us some tea, regaled us with cookies, and introduced us to her dog, her husband and two beautiful kids. After hearing our story, Dasha said we could stay at her place as long as we need until we settle down. With her help, we were able to find a rental place in the next few days. My dad went back home. He left me all the money. It was enough for me to buy trolley bus tickets and buckwheat groats until I got my first paycheck.</p>

<p>This was a life changing experiences for me, and a great lesson. We have been friends with Dasha and her family ever since. I am very grateful for our friendship. She and her family have moved to U.S. recently, so we are neighbors again. Her kids have grown up now. Oh, the time is flying so quickly…</p>

<p>Catch every single moment of life.</p>

<p>Enjoy it as long as you can.</p>

<p>Never give up.</p>

<p>Help each other.</p>

<p>Be happy!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
